Register of the Grigorii Nikolaevich Trubetskoi papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- [B.1. r-2, s-3, b-25, f. 2 Razlichnye korotkie publikatsii], d. 22 (Reading room Workstation)
  Offprints of various short articles written by G. N. Trubetskoi, including: "Das Schisma in Sowjetrussland" (38 pages), "Spor o monarkhii" (4 pages), P. P. Izvol'skii, "K voprosu o soedinenii tserkvei" (Munich, 1922), and various additional pamphlets
- [B.1. r-2, s-3, b-3, f-5 Vyrezki. Kn. G. N. Trubetskoi, "Slovo," 1908] - NOT RECEIVED, d. 23
  Newspaper clippings of articles by G. N. Trubetskoi from Slovo, primarily on the Balkans in 1908.
  This file, containing 99 pages, was not received by the Hoover Institution.
- [B.1. r-2, s-3, b-2, f-2 Tserkovnye gazetnye vyrezki, nachalo 19-20 (Arkhiv G. N. Trubetskogo)], 1919-1920; d. 24 (Reading room Workstation)
  Newspaper clippings from various newspapers on church matters
- [B.1. r-2, s-3, b-25, f-9 Jurisdictional difference newspaper clippings, etc.], d. 25 (Reading room Workstation)
  Various newspaper clippings in Russian, Polish, and French
- [B.1. r-2, s-3, b-24, f-8 Razlichnye prizyvy i ukazy gen. Vrangelia (vo vremia) Krymskoi kampanii], 1920; d. 26 (Reading room Workstation)
  Various regulations, orders, decrees from General Vrangel
- [B.1. r-2, s-3, b-26, f-1 Razlichnye documenty (ne razobrannye) 1920s], d. 27 (Reading room Workstation)
  Various documents and letters regarding Church money, holidays, and traditions
- [B.1. r-2, s-3, b-26, f-3 Perevod na angliiskii i frantzuskii iazyik], d. 28 (Reading room Workstation)
  Draft translation of Trubetskoi's 1914 memoir into English and French (143 pages)
- [B.1. r-2, s-4, b-28, f-28. Razlichnye pis'ma k G. N. Trubetskomu (podpisannye)], 1920s; d. 29 (Reading room Workstation)
  Copies of letters to G. N. Trubetskoi. Letter from Jules Scriban (in French), Berlin, February 15, 1921. A pamphlet by Grigorii Trubetskoi in the memory of Cardinal Mersie. A letter to Princess Maria Troubetzkoy (Belgrade) from Albert Wolf ( Newark, NJ), April 16, 1925. A letter from Lord Shaftesbury to unknown person, May 29, 1924. Attached letter to the editor: "For the Russian Church. The Hope of the Future." A copy of a letter from "Sillogizm," August 2, 1923, on the church abroad. S. Orlov to Trubetskoi on religious topics, March 14, 1927. A. Lisarubkin to Trubetskoi from Rome, December 10, 1920. M. Osorgin to Trubetskoi, June 15, Moscow. Reaction to the death of Archbishop Aleksei. S. Malash to Trubetskoi, January 30, 1929, Budapest. Church and emigration to Hungary.
- [B1. r-2, s-3, b-28, f-29 Mitropolit Anastasii. K 40-letiiu ego verkhovnogo sluzheniia. "Tserkovnaia letopis'," 1946], d. 30 (Reading room Workstation)
  Article celebrating the 40th anniversary in service of Metropolitan Anastasii
- [B1. Unnamed], 1910s-1920s; d. 31 (Reading room Workstation)
  Various articles and notes. Draft chapter on the conditions of the Orthodox Parish, undated. Document with accounts of battles, Petrograd, January 20-21, 1915. A summary of a military meeting, March 6, 1920. A summary of Wilson's Fourteen Points. A. F. Kruglov to Russian envoy in Egypt on the Russian Orthodox Church in Jerusalem, August 25, 1920. "O merakh k ob"edineniiu Russkikh pravoslavnykh khristian v stranakh zapadnoi Evropy," copy, no author, undated.
- [B1. r-2, s-3, b-26, f-4 Ocherk vzaimnootnoshenii Frantsii i iuga Rossii. May 1919], d. 32 (Reading room Workstation)
  Ocherk vzaimootnoshenii vooruzhennykh sil Iuga Rossii Predstavitelei Frantsuzskogo Komandovaniia Mai 1919 goda. Sovershenno sekretno. (Ekaterinodar: Upravlenie Gen. Kvartirmeistera Shtaba Glavnokomanduiushchogo Vooruzhennymi Silami na Iuge Rossii, 1919), 43 pages
- [B.1. r-2, s-3, b-27, f-4 The British Trade Union Delegation and the Situation in (the) Soviet Union], undated; d. 33 (Reading room Workstation)
  A typed report sharply condemning the report published by the British Trade Union Delegation on conditions in the Soviet Union. No author, undated. 32 pages
- [B.1. r-2, s-3, b-27, f-6 Sibirskii Vostok 1920kh godov.], d. 34 (Reading room Workstation)
  Manuscript by I. I. Sukin on the conditions in Russia during the civil war (pages 3-300)
- [B.1. r-2, s-5, b-26, f-5 Dorevolutsionnaia gazeta, pravitel'stvennye publikatsii (P.B. Struve i drugie)] - NOT RECEIVED, circa 1905; d. 35
  Pravo, vols. 33-35 (1905). Osvobozhdenie (published by Struve), no. 7 (September 18, 1903), no. 20 (March 19, 1904). Revolutsionnaia Rossiia, no. 72 (August 1, 1905). Osvobozhdenie, no. 5 (August 19, 1903); no. 22 (May 8, 1903); no. 55 (September 2, 1904). Iskra, no. 108 (July 13,1905). Proletarii, no. 12 (August 16, 1905).
  This file, containing an unknown number of pages, was not received by the Hoover Institution. The file is available only at GARF.
- [B.1, r-2, s-3, b-27, f-3. Razlichnye vospominaniia i takogo zhe roda publikatsii], circa 1880-1920; d. 36 (Reading room Workstation)
  "Echos Du Passe," 22 pages, 2 copies. A copy of a book about illustrations in Russian tales. Concentrates on D.I. Mitrokhin, in English, by M. Kouzmin. "Petergofskaia doroga v starinu i v poslednee vremia," 12 pages. Pamphlet describing the duties of the government and Russian citizens (no author, location, likely in 1919). Essay critical of the communist party (no author, location, likely in 1919). A story about hunting (most likely fictional, no date, author). A script to a play by S. N. Trubetskoi performed in Kaluga. ("Poslednoe Slovo Nauki," June 23, 1886).
- [B.1, r-2, s-3, b-28, f-28. 1 of 2. Pis'ma Mitropolita Anastasiia k G. N. Trubetskomu.], d. 37 (Reading room Workstation)
  8 letters from Metropolitan Anastasii to G. N. Trubetskoi on church matters and the Soviet government
- [B. 1, r-2, s-3, b-28, f-29. 2 of 2. Pis'ma ot i k Mitropolitu Anastasiiu. Arkhiv G. N. Trubetskogo.], 1920s; d. 38 (Reading room Workstation)
  Correspondence between Metropolitan Anastasii and G. N. Trubetskoi
- [B. 1, r-2, s-3, b-28, f-4. Pis'ma Mitropolita Platona k G. N. Trubetskomu], 1926; d. 39 (Reading room Workstation)
  2 letters from Metropolitan Platon to G. N. Trubetskoi
- [B. 1, r-2, s-3, b-28, f-3. Pis'ma Mitropolita Evlogiia k G. N. Trubetskomu], 1926-1928; d. 40 (Reading room Workstation)
  Letters to G. N. Trubetskoi from Metropolitan Evlogiia on conflicts among metropolitans. Paris
- [B.1, r-2, s-3, b-28, f-1. Pis'ma Mitropolita Antoniia k G. N. Trubetskomu], 1920s; d. 41 (Reading room Workstation)
  Letter from Metropolitan Antonii to G. N. Trubetskoi on the imprisonment of metropolitans in the Soviet Union, August 11, 1926. "Otvet Mitropolita Antoniia byvshemu episkopu Evdokimu."
- [B 1, r-2, s-3, b-28, f-11. Fotokopii pisem G. N. Trubetskogo k Petru Berngardovichu Struve, 1924-1972. Frantsiia], 1926-1928; d. 42 (Reading room Workstation)
  Correspondence between G. N. Trubetskoi and Peter Struve regarding politics and church matters (copies). A letter from Struve to S. S. Efremov, February 9, 1927, Paris.
- [B.1., r-2, s-3, b-28, f-7. Razlichnye tserkovnye pis'ma k G. N. Trubetskomu.], 1922-1927; d. 43 (Reading room Workstation)
  Letters to Trubetskoi on church affairs
- [B.1, r-2, s-3, b-28, f-6. Kopii doklada 1928 Mitropolita Elevferiia k Mitropolitu Evlogiiu.], 1989 November 7; d. 44 (Reading room Workstation)
  Letter to Sergei Grigorievich Troubetzkoy from Archbishop Sylvester, St. Peter and Paul Russian Orthodox Cathedral, Montreal
- [B.1, r-2, s-3, b-28, f-15. Pis'ma S. D. Sazonovu (byvshii ministr inostrannykh del)], 1919-1928; d. 45 (Reading room Workstation)
  A letter to Anna Borisovna from G. N. Trubetskoi regarding metropolitans Sergei and Evlogii, July 3, 1928. Two letters to S. D. Sazonov from G. N. Trubetskoi on the relationship between church and state, October 16, 1919, and February 22, 1920.
- [B.1, r-2, s-5, b-28, f-14. Pis'ma M. Girsa, byvshego posla v Parizhe], 1926-1927; d. 46 (Reading room Workstation)
  Letters on church affairs from the former ambassador in Paris, M. Girs, to G. N. Trubetskoi
- [B.1, r-2, s-2, b-28, f-13. Pis'ma I. Nazhivina k G. N. Trubetskomu 1921], d. 47 (Reading room Workstation)
  Letters from I. Nazhivin to G. N. Trubetskoi with reactions to Trubetskoi's articles. Constantinople
- [r-2, s-5, b-28, f-10. Pis'ma Vasiliia Shtrandtmana iz Belgrada, Serbia, k kn.G. N. Trubetskomu], 1921-1927; d. 48 (Reading room Workstation)
  Letters to G. N. Trubetskoi from V. Shtrandtman on Russian Orthodox churches and officials abroad. Belgrade
- [B.1, r-2, s-3, b-28, f-9. Pis'ma (kopii) G. N. Trubetskogo], 1926-1927; d. 49 (Reading room Workstation)
  Two letters in French from G. N. Trubetskoi to Mr. Kullman, July 30, 1926, and March 15, 1926
  Correspondence between G. N. Trubetskoi and his mother, 1926-1927
- [B.1, r-2, s-3, b-28, f-5. Doklad velikomu kniazu Nikolai Nikol. (Romanovu) i "mysli" velikogo kniazia N.N. i pis'ma], circa 1926; d. 50 (Reading room Workstation)
  Two copies of a 7-page report to Grand Duke Nikolai Nikolaevich Romanov written by G. N. Trubetskoi, July 27, 1926, Vosges
  "Neskol'ko myslei" (7 pp). Memo of Grand Duke Nikolai Nikolaevich explaining his politics in the emigration from 1917 to June 1926. Marked "confidential, for personal use."
- [B.1, r-2, s-5, b-28, f-12. Pis'ma S. Botkina (Delo Russkogo bratstva v Berline) k G. N. Trubetskomu], 1925-1928; d. 51 (Reading room Workstation)
  Letters from S. Botkin to G. N. Trubetskoi on the Vladimir Brotherhood (Vladimirskoe bratstvo), Berlin, 1925, 1928
- [B. 1, r-2, s-3, b-24, f-5. Gazetnye vyrezki], 1926; d. 52 (Reading room Workstation)
  Various pamphlets, newspaper clippings on the emigration, the church, the controversy about Metropolitan Evlogii
- [f2 Lzheimennaia tserkov' v Rossii. Rukopis' Kn. G. N. Trubetskogo], d. 53 (Reading room Workstation)
  A description of the Living Church in the USSR by G. N. Trubetskoi accompanied by newspaper clippings and data on repressions of priests and the church in the USSR
- [f3. Conference de Washington], 1921 December 14; d. 54 (Reading room Workstation)
  A newspaper clipping from a French newspaper on a Washington conference on Belgian interests in China
- [f 7. Kn. G. N. Trubetskoi. Rukopis' "Istoriia Russkoi diplomatii"], undated; d. 55 (Reading room Workstation)
  "Znachenie vneshnei politiki v istorii Rossii i ee glavnye zadachi." Handwritten manuscript about the relations between Russia and Europe by G. N. Trubetskoi
- [Nachalo voiny, 1914. Vospominaniia kn. G. N. Trubetskogo], d. 56 (Reading room Workstation)
  Typed manuscript later published as: Russkaia diplomatiia, 1914-1917 g.g. i voina na Balkanakh (Montreal: Bratstvo prep. I. Pochaevskogo, 1983)
- [f.3. "Istoricheskie zametki", zapisi kn. G. N. Trubetskogo], d. 57 (Reading room Workstation)
  Notes taken by Trubetskoi in three notebooks
- [f.4. Razlichnye documenty, programma lektsii, pis'ma. G. N. Trubetskoi], 1927 November 20; d. 58 (Reading room Workstation)
  Lectures about Russia
- [f.1. Serbia, 1915-1916. Kn. G. N. Trubetskoi], d. 59 (Reading room Workstation)
  A letter to Trubetskoi from Dr. Sergei K. Sofoterov explaining the conditions in Serbia, December 29, 1926
  A document describing how to treat the wounded. No author, location. Undated
- [f .8. Nekhvataiushchie stranitsy kn. G. N. Trubetskogo], d. 60 (Reading room Workstation)
  Various draft articles and notes on disparate themes. Includes notes for lectures on the history of Russian diplomacy, a draft article or lecture on "zadachi tserkvi v bezhentstve," copy of a letter to Patriarch Tikhon
- [f. 11. Razlichnye chernoviki statei i rechei. Kn. Gr. N. Trubetskoi, 1919-1928.], d. 61 (Reading room Workstation)
  Various draft articles, speeches, and notes by G. N. Trubetskoi
- [f. 5. Zapiski kn. G. N. Trubetskogo. Kurs russkoi istorii.], d. 62 (Reading room Workstation)
  Lecture notes prepared by G. N. Trubetskoi for a course on Russian history
- [r-2, s-4, b-24, f-14. Obliki Proshlogo. Family memories.], 1925 Fall; d. 63 (Reading room Workstation)
  G. N. Trubetskoi's handwritten memoirs and family history. "Obliki Proshlogo" (see d. 104 for a typed version)
  Sem'ia moego otsa, pages 2-18
  Sem'ia moiei materi, pages 18-31
  Diadia Seriozha, pages 31-51
  Moi roditeli, pages 52-68
  Kaluga, pages 68-79
  Nashi druz'ia, pages 80-89
  Gimnaziia, pages 90-91
  Kaluzhskoe obshchestvo, pages 91-96
  Sergievskoe, pages 97-99
  Brat Serezha, pages 100-105
  Moskva: Presnia, pages 106-134
  Moskovskii universitet (1892-1896), pages 135-169
  Staryi vostok (otryvki vospominanii) (17 pages). Section on the early part of Trubetskoi's career
- [f. 1-12. La Revue Catholique (Brusselles) 4 stat'i kn. G. N. Trubetskogo.] - NOT RECEIVED, 1922-1924; d. 64
  Four complete issues of the newspaper "La Revue Catholique," March 28, 1924; November 17, 1922; February 17, 1922; January 27, 1922. Clipping from "La Libre Belgique," from December 2, 1921, article on Trubetskoi.
  This file, containing an unknown number of pages, was not received by the Hoover Institution. The file is only available at GARF.
- [f-3 Gazeta ("Rossiia" P. B. Struve, "Pamiati gen. P. N. Vrangelia" 1928] - NOT RECEIVED, 1928 May 5; d. 65
  Newspaper "Rossiia," no. 35. Featuring an article in memory of Gen. Vrangel.
  This file, containing an unknown number of pages, was not received by the Hoover Institution.
- [B. 3, f-4 "Tseli voiny," fotokopii stat'i kn. G. N. Trubetskogo.], 1917 January; d. 66 (Reading room Workstation)
  Photocopy of a 40-page article by Trubetskoi outlining the aims of WWI to N. N. Pokrovskii on January 10, 1917, with copy of 11-page addendum sent on January 14, 1917
- [r-2, s-3, b-28, f-7. Newspapers. G. N.], d. 67 (Reading room Workstation)
  Newspaper clippings of articles by G. N. Trubetskoi in memory of Cardinal Mercie, on the new Turkish constitution, and on church finances
- [B.3, f-2. Rukopisnye zapiski kn. G. N. Trubetskogo.], 1920s-1930s; d. 68 (Reading room Workstation)
  Handwritten notes on the Russian Orthodox Church and other topics
- [B.3, f-6. Podpisannye pis'ma G. N. Trubetskogo.], 1926-1927; d. 69 (Reading room Workstation)
  Various letters to and from G. N. Trubetskoi, including several regarding Patriarch Tikhon
- [f-6. Vospominaniia kn. G. N. Trubetskogo "Kiev, Ukraina, Ekaterinodar, 1919."], 1918-1919; d. 70 (Reading room Workstation)
  Handwritten diary by G. N. Trubetskoi in Kiev and Ekaterinodar
- [B.3, f-8. G. N. Trubetskoi. Varia notes.], undated; d. 71 (Reading room Workstation)
  Various typed notes of G. N. Trubetskoi about his life. In Russian and French
- [B.3. f. 9. Pis'mo (P.) Krasnova k imperatoru Vil'gelmu.], 1918 August; d. 72 (Reading room Workstation)
  Copy of a letter from Ataman P. Krasnov to the Emperor of Germany asking him for help after the Russian Revolution
- [B.3, f-10. Nepodpisannye dokumenty kn. G. N. Trubetskogo.], 1916-1927; d. 73 (Reading room Workstation)
  Various documents on the conditions of the church and state in Serbia and other countries
- [f-5. Pis'ma S. Ugeta (S. Ughet) k kn. G. N. Trubetkomu i drugie (documenty). USA-Europe], 1924-1926; d. 74 (Reading room Workstation)
  Correspondence and documents on a lawsuit in New York brought by John S. Kedrovsky of the Living Church in an attempt to gain legal recognition of his title as "metropolitan" of North America and to gain the legal control of the property of the church in North America
- [B.3. f-9. Beseda velikogo kniaza Nikolaia Nikolaevicha (Romanova) s predstavitelem amerikanskoi pechati na Paskhe 1924 g.], d. 75 (Reading room Workstation)
  7 copies of a leaflet published by Tip. "Franko-Russkaia Pechat'," Paris
- [B.3., f-13. Kopiia pis'ma atamana P. Krasnova imperatoru Vl'gel'mu], d. 76 (Reading room Workstation)
- [B.3. f. 14. Zapisi grafa K.A. Buteneva na osnovanii dokladov kn. G. N. Trubetskogo.], 1918 August; d. 77 (Reading room Workstation)
  Notes regarding the formation of the Russian Army to fight against Germany, no author. Written in August 8/21, 1918.
- [B.3, f. 15, f-17. Doklad Metropolitu Evlogiu ot "Sillogizma"], 1923 June 2; d. 78 (Reading room Workstation)
  Letter to Metropolitan Evlogii from "Sillogizm" on Archbishop Tikhon, Moscow
- [ f-16. L' Union des Eglises selon la pensée orthodoxe.], 1924; d. 79 (Reading room Workstation)
  Typed manuscript by G. Kolémine, "L' Union des Eglises selon la pensée orthodoxe," Paris
- [ B.3, f-9 Starye (1908) stat'i kn. G. N. Trubetskogo.], d. 80 (Reading room Workstation)
  Newspaper clippings of articles written by Trubetskoi
- [B.3, f-1. Vospominaniia kniazhny Ol'gi N. Trubetskoi.], d. 81 (Reading room Workstation)
  The history of the Trubetskoi family by Olga N. Trubetskaia. Typescript
- [B. 3, f-10. Razlichnye rukopisi kn. G. N. Trubetskogo.], 1920s; d. 82 (Reading room Workstation)
  Various handwritten notes, prayers, and religious thoughts of G. N. Trubetskoi
- [Razlichnye russkie starye karty (geograficheskie), f7] - NOT RECEIVED, d. 83
  Collection of Russian maps, most from World War I.
- [R-2, F-3, B. 26, F-6. Vospominaniia kn. Gr. N. Trubetskogo s 1914 goda po 1916 god, kopiia.], d. 84 (Reading room Workstation)
  Untitled typed book manuscript. Memoiristic account of Trubetskoi's work interpreting diplomacy in the Balkans. 246 pages. Later published as Russkaia diplomatiia, 1914-1917 g.g. i voina na Balkanakh (Montreal: Bratstvo prep. i. Pochaevskogo, 1983)
- [R-2, S-3, B-23, F-3. Lichnye dokumenty Mikh.Gr. Trubetskogo. Diplomy, etc.], 1900s; d. 85 (Reading room Workstation)
  Personal documents and correspondence of G.N. Trubetskoi's son, Mikhail Grigorievich Troubetzkoi, including:
  An invitation from Hoover Institution at Stanford, California to hold the archives of Grigorii Trubetskoi, August 23, 1985, pages 2-3
  Diplomas of Mikhail Gr. Troubetzkoi, pages 4-14
  A letter to the Emperor from P. Krasnov, August 1918, on conditions in the Don region during the Civil War, pages 24-27
  Unmarked text on the church after the Civil War and the Bolshevik Revolution, undated, pages 29-30
  A letter to Mikhail Troubetzkoi offering to help with the publication of G. N. Trubetskoi's book "Ocherki vzaimootnoshii vooruzhennykh sil iuga Rossii," Ottawa, November 8, 1981, p. 32
  A letter about a settlement proceeding, September 18, 1925, Vienna, pages 33-35
- [R-2, S-3, B-23, F-2. Kopiia. Chast' vtoraia "Vybory Patriarkha."], d. 86 (Reading room Workstation)
  Typed manuscript "Lzheimennaia tserkov v SSSR" (pages 1-49) and notes and materials for other articles
- [R-2, S-3, B-23, F-5. Stat'i, gazety, pias'ma, etc.], 1920s; d. 87 (Reading room Workstation)
  Large collection of newspaper clippings, primarily from the émigré press on the church in the Soviet Union in the 1920s
  Correspondence between M. N. Girs and Russian Financial Attaché S. Ughet regarding the lawsuit of Ivan Kedrovskii against Metropolitan Platon, December 1924, pages 147-150
- [r-2, s-3, b-23, f-4. Razlichnye fotokopii (dokumentov) kn. Mih. Gr. Troubetskogo], early 1900s; d. 88 (Reading room Workstation)
  Original documents and photocopies, includes drafts of articles and book chapters by Grigorii Trubetskoi. Includes article "Krestnyi put' nashei tserkvi, 1917-1927," large collection of newspaper clippings on Tikhon in 1925-1926
- [R-2, s-3, B-25, F-8. Otkrytie tserkovnogo vserossiiskogo Sobora, 1917. "Posledovanie," Sergei Troubetzkoy], 1917 August 28; d. 89 (Reading room Workstation)
  Church prayer dedicated to the opening of the All-Russian Orthodox Church Council in Moscow (4 pages)
- [r-2, s-3, b-24, F-3. Gazety- Vyrezki 20 godov.] - NOT RECEIVED, 1920s; d. 90
  Various newspaper clippings. This file, containing an unknown number of pages, was not received by the Hoover Institution. It is available only at the OCA Archives.
- [R-2, S-3, B-24, F-4. Inostrannye gazety vo vremya Belogo dvizhenia.] - NOT RECEIVED, 1919-1921; d. 91
  Various émigré newspaper clippings on the White movement.
  This file, containing an unknown number of pages, was not received by the Hoover Institution. It is available only at the OCA Archives.
- [R-2, S-3, B-24, F-2. Vyrezki gazet Dobrovol'cheskoi armii] - NOT RECEIVED, 1917-1920s; d. 92
  Various newspaper clippings and whole newspapers, primarily on the Volunteer Army in Russia during the civil war.
- [R-2, S-3, B-27, F-5. Gazetnye (tserkov') vyrezki 20kh godov] - NOT RECEIVED, 1920s; d. 93
  Various newspaper clippings and whole newspapers on church matters.
- [R-2, S-3, B-23, F-1. Pis'ma kn. Mikhaila Gr. Trubetskogo], d. 94 (Reading room Workstation)
  Correspondence of Mikhail Grigorievich Troubetzkoy, including
  A letter to Mikhail Trubetzkoy from Ksenia Denikina asking him for part of the archives of G. N. Trubetskoi, November 14, 1950, New York, pages 2-3
  Correspondence on the publication of G. N. Trubetskoi's book "Gody smut i nadezhd", including 1980-1981 correspondence with Alexander Solzhenitsyn
- [Grigorii Trubetskoi. His report to the Grand Duke N. N. and P. Krasnov's letter to German Emperor Wilhelm], d. 95 (Reading room Workstation)
  Copy of Krasnov's August 1918 report on the takeover of the Don territory by the White forces.
  A letter from Troubetskoi to the Grand Duke asking him to get involved in church politics, July 27, 1926
- [r-2, s-5, b-28, f-8. Tserkov'. Pis'ma iz Ameriki k kn. Gr. N. Trubetskomu], d. 96 (Reading room Workstation)
  Collection of correspondence to Trubetskoi in Paris from America dealing with church matters in North America and about Patriarch Tikhon
- [Photocopies of the correspondence of Trubetskoi and Rev. Michel D'Herbigny.], d. 97 (Reading room Workstation)
  Correspondence between Trubetskoi and Herbigny. Also includes some of the latter's writings on his ideas to unify the Catholic and Orthodox churches
- Arreté de l'assembleé national le 20 ? 1830 au patriarcat armenien á Constantinople pour la reformation du clerge, des institutions et des communes - NOT RECEIVED, d. 98
  Original document.
- [Pis'ma Pere Michel d'Herbigny. Originaly. F. 11], d. 99 (Reading room Workstation)
  Correspondence between Trubetskoi and Herbigny. Includes some of the latter's writings on his ideas to unify the Catholic and Orthodox churches. Also includes letters from G. N. Trubetskoi to Archbishop Anastasii about possible unification of the Orthodox and Catholic churches in common opposition to the Bolsheviks, pages 93-117
- [R-2, S-5, B-25, F-1. Razlichnye fotokopii 20kh godov. Tserkovnye dela], 1920s; d. 100 (Reading room Workstation)
  Large collection of photocopies of documents, articles, and newspaper clippings on church matters
- Mitropolit Elevferii, Nedelia v Patriarkhii (vpechatleniia i nabliudeniia ot poezdki v Moskvu) (Paris: Pravoslavnoe izd.) - NOT RECEIVED, 1933; d. 101
  This file, containing 158 pages plus appendices, was not received by the Hoover Institution. It is available at the OCA Archives and in libraries.
- [R-2, S-3, B-25, F. 6] - NOT RECEIVED, 1920s; d. 102
  Bound collection of documents, articles, and Trubetskoi's article on the Living Church, Tikhon, and other issues in the church during the 1920s
- Sophie Schmitz. "Grigori N. Trubetzkoy: Politik und Völkerrecht, 1873-1930." Unpublished Ph.D. dissertation, University of Vienna, 1971; d. 103 (Reading room Workstation)
  General note
  When citing, please include the full dissertation reference.
- Obliki proshlogo, 1925 Fall; d. 104 (Reading room Workstation)